all right welcome to community learn
number four before we start I'd like to
just thank some people and I we talked
about it at the Lamia but some of you
weren't here and the history of these
cottages that you're staying in is that
we had a seven year course here in
Vajrayana starting 2003 and three or
four then we went until 2010 and then a
group of the students went into a three
year silent retreat and they built their
own comments with their own money and
then they said after we finish our
three-year retreat we will offer our
cabins to Diamond Mountain for free and
so future generations like you can stay
in them and we have some of them are
here today and I'd like to ask if they
could stand people who did the three
retreat
[Music]
[Applause]
some of them built two houses and gave
them to diamond I'd also like to ask the
staff to stand up Michael and Melissa
and there's other stuff
[Music]
[Applause]
and thank you for them they worked
really hard all year getting ready for
us and the day before you get here
everything breaks and then they spend
the whole retreat fixing things so thank
you for that and I hope you learn to
love this place like we do and I hope
you will think about don't I mean of
course come in the spring in the fall
for these long memory treats we have
about I don't know we probably have
another 20 to go and then but also
please consider this your home in
America and anytime you want to come and
do a retreat three days three years or
something between then please come and
just do your own between okay and it's
hard to find such a beautiful place in
such a quiet place we chose the quietest
place the United States you can't even
get cell phone service there in the
valley and it was hard to find a place
like that so although we we just put in
internet because we thought if there's
an emergency you should be able to call
one of the staff but I'm sure you won't
use the internet for anything else okay
it's it you spend a lot of money and a
lot of time to get here and if you use
the internet you're a little bit crazy
okay so I ask you keep silence except
during class if I ask for questions and
then keep silence during this retreat
and you will have a better retreat you
will have a good
retreat okay Reis in recent years since
those guys did their long retreat we've
improved the place a lot we we bought
more land now the land is quite it's I
think it's the largest retreat center in
the United States and maybe one of the
largest in the world and we were able to
build this Student Center which fits I
think 200 150 185 legally for dinner and
we're about to put in a million dollars
worth of roads starting in the next few
months and a lot of that is possible due
to one person a very kind person who's
been helping us and I'd like to thank
dr. mung Fong
[Music]
[Applause]
he's very patient every time I see him I
squeeze him and his wife is here and his
sister-in-law is here I'd like to
welcome her
all right so by the way were handing out
the diamond cutter Sutra it's finished
it's in four languages a lot of work I
started this 20 years ago and we just
finished it I think yesterday and it's
in four languages jing-mei worked really
hard on the Sanskrit and Stanley Chen
worked really hard on the Chinese I
think he didn't sleep for some time and
it was a lot of work for many years and
so now it's ready and we printed a nice
one for you to keep for the rest of your
life because Geshe Michael didn't finish
until two days ago we had to pay the
printer what do you call it a ransom and
Veronica and I have paid a thousand and
jing-mei paid five hundred but I need
one thousand more from three people
raise your hand one two three finished
the rest of you are too slow
talk to Tim okay and so we just offer it
to me buddy okay
did you catch the three if you didn't
it's you okay and this has all the four
comma less user classes in it all the
meditations if you missed one of the
four classes courses then you can catch
up with one of the people who did do it
and I encourage you to teach it to each
other the ones you missed and you
shouldn't you should try to catch up
okay and we've been doing comics either
for two years now and we're gonna finish
this week and I think it's the first
time in a thousand years anyone has
thought comma zero
[Applause]
and that's the biggest commentary on the
diamond cutter from India there's one
very small one by Vasa bundle and
Camilla Sheila incorporates most of us
in bandar so if you know Camilla Sheila
you know the tradition from India okay
there's one great commentary in Tibet by
Tony Lama ACI course six has a lot of it
and we're working by the end of January
we'll finish that commentary in English
but with the translation programs that
we have around the world and those are
also funded by mr. Wu largely and I'd
like to thank him again
and we also have a strong support from
Germany and Austria Renata baguette has
been helping a lot in Norbert and
Jessica from Germany
and the Viet Nam group which is very
large there are 1500 students done
studying there and they are supporting
the translators also so I'd like to
thank them
all right then
so because you need to meditate starting
tomorrow morning we're going to start
with a meditation tonight and then we're
gonna start at the end of the diamond
cutter Sutra which is the most famous
part of the diamond cutter Sutra which
is the mantra at the end of the Sutra
and it's the main meditations for you
guys this week you actually have two
main meditations this week one is the
dance of the lion which many of you did
in the lamrim course some of you were
asleep I think I like it because you
have jet lag and I don't so this is the
only place in the world say sing huh
virgin betta sing huh vision PETA okay
that's the name of the meditation we're
going to focus on and during this week
okay those of you who came to LA mmm you
did it with me
you know it well sing hum means lion
like Singapore poor means city singer
means lion and Singapore city of the
Lions
there are lion fundraisers anyway and
vision betta means okay
that's the only translation it means you
know what's that American movie company
the lion comes first and goes yeah then
it means the lion is roaring at your
negative emotions okay and your
obstacles to Buddhahood
so in American English it would be a bad
word and I can't say it because
Veronica's here
and you'd have a special sign with your
hand and it literally means that it
means when doubts come to you when
trouble comes to you when you don't
understand the jinkin gene diamond
cutter Sutra then you go look at those
negative thoughts and the name of the
meditation is dancing vigil beta means
in the Russian you say groan yeah girl
groan Thunder it comes from the same
root German okay so it means so that
meditation was taught by Lord Buddha I
found that five times in the ancient
books from India he taught it five times
that I can find he taught it in the
hundred thousand verses of Babylon medo
approach the parameter and he taught it
in the twenty thousand verses and 18,000
verses and he taught it in two other
sutras so we're gonna do that Maitreya
also taught it and it's in the obvious
sanam mile Ankara just the name it says
[Music]
Nene singing I'm game betting engine on
young-soon a tangent engine loop to Don
do meet on the top edge a very famous
line by Maitreya so Maitreya taught it
just before you do meditation on the
wheel of life okay so I've been teaching
it I started in Mexico there are five
parts to the dance of the Nile we did
the first part in Mexico last summer
this summer last summer
then last week we did the second part
for the first time here okay and in the
future we have to learn three more parts
okay
mr. Wu's gonna we're gonna put together
a translation of it the whole thing okay
in his free time and I've made about a
hundred and like two hundred pages of
notes about it
from the scriptures and it's very
beautiful so I'd like to start with that
tonight just for good luck okay you are
tired you traveled today you're in a
strange place you're gonna wake up
tonight and try to find your
refrigerator and you will probably find
a bear so I won't do too much let's just
do for good luck okay
tonight we'll do a little bit there are
eight stages of that meditation to climb
up to the meditations so it's like
taking an elevator eight floors up you
go past eight floors you don't you just
use it to climb it's a deeper and deeper
meditation more and more quiet so each
time you go up to the next floor it's
more quiet than the floor before and
those first eight meditations are just
like a ladder to get to the ninth one
then the ninth when is the real
meditation okay and in this tradition
it's very famous that you shouldn't stop
on the first eight floors and I'd like
to compare it to there's a restaurant in
sorry there's a hotel in Kiev what it
calls good
what's the whole hotel called premier
palace we always stay there we had a
nice group from Kia they did the
emptiness course together diamond-cut of
course how many how many people for 50
people for two days in the hotel then on
the ninth floor of the hotel is Roma
cafe cafe Roma it's a nice restaurant
okay
and if you get off on the first eight
floors you there's nothing to eat
okay understand so the first eight steps
in this meditation are not a golf they
are not meditation really they are just
warming up for the Olympics okay there's
no Olympic gold medal for warming up
okay you have to run okay so love of
mine which is where the restaurant is
right in the what's it called paradise
premier palace so when you get to ninth
floor you get out but you have to go up
through eight floors okay now I like to
tell people in Europe it's very
confusing for American because in
America the first floor is the first
floor but in Europe the first floor is
the second floor and they count the
lowest floor is zero okay then the
second floor is called 1ok and Herald
it's not so weird in America there's no
13th floor because it's unlucky number
so that goes from 12 to 14 it's very
confusing okay so just like a European
hotel there's a beginning place in the
meditation which we can call zero zero
is at zero level you listen to a sound
in the room you try to connect with a
sound in the room and this is called
desire around we live in the desire
realm and so in this meditation you
don't count your breath before you
meditate
you go straight to a distraction okay if
you don't have a distraction in your
house you can buy a loud air-conditioner
or refrigerator I have a noisy
refrigerator it's very good for this
meditation if you live in Guangzhou or
something
you have the traffic outside you're very
lucky if you have kids it's automatic
you you have noise in the house okay
Ella you're lucky and okay so zero floor
is desire room and you start the
meditation by listening to some noise in
the room okay
hopefully the person next to you in this
room will decide to drink or something
or go or maybe they forget to turn off
their form if you're very lucky and you
can listen to this noise okay so there's
always some small noises in the room
okay then you go through four
meditations we call form realm
meditations I'll explain it tomorrow and
then you go through for meditation is
called formless realm meditations okay
and let's do a quick run through the
eighth okay just to irritate you since
you have jet lag I love to see you so
study because I feel that way most of
the year and this is my real revenge
to make you meditate on the first night
after a big dinner it's almost
impossible okay so here we go get ready
turn off your phone
Buddha said the first part of meditation
is to turn off your phone
the Mexico group charge you $50 if your
phone goes off it's expensive is it too
warm in here is it okay
should I freeze you everybody say no
freeze you raise your hand yeah you lose
I'll freeze you tomorrow
if you sit here or here tomorrow wear a
coat okay because we have a this air
conditioner comes from the same woody
call tongue ciao air conditioner it was
made during tongue ciao it was made in
the time of SH went on and come alive
Sheila okay
it's a little bit noisy it makes
everyone hear cold and it doesn't heat
the people it doesn't it doesn't reach
the back okay okay just a quick trip
through the first eight floors we don't
get off of the elevator till tomorrow so
first
the sounds in the room there is an air
conditioner esta
and try to glue your mind to that thumb
keep your mind touching that Sun and
we'll stay here for 10 breaths 15
breaths just listen to the sound of the
air conditioner try not to think about
other things
compared to that sound the sound of your
heartbeat is more quiet so we go up the
elevator to the next floor first floor
and at the first floor first level we
listen to the sound of our heartbeat
each level we will go more quiet to a
more quiet place and then on the ninth
floor we will go deep into the teachings
on emptiness which is the goal but here
at the first floor we just listen to her
heart when you're alone in a diamond
mountain cottage you can actually hear
your heartbeat in your in your eardrums
here in a group
you might have to just feel your
heartbeat in your chest so for me it's
like I feel like I'm in my head
and I'm looking down at my heart and I
can feel my heart beating so let's Bend
let's first go to the air-conditioner
sound and then purposely take the
elevator up quieter place which is the
sound of your heartbeat or the feel of
your heartbeat in your chest as you look
down at your chest in your mind
watching your heartbeat it would be more
quiet to go inside your heart and sit
inside your heart like a little rumor
little chamber and feel the heart
beating around you maybe you're even
part of the heartbeat so now go to the
second level second floor and the
elevator and it's more quiet in the
hardest beating around you almost you
are beating each time you move
another level you should try to get more
and more quiet in your mind
to the being inside the beating heart it
would be almost more quiet to let the
heart beat without you as if it were far
away and alone
just by itself beating in a very quiet
place and we are not there so see if you
can imagine the heart beating a little
bit far away and you are no longer
connected to it it's very quietly
beating in an empty place
level we try to imagine in the place of
our heart we dropped the heart and we
try to imagine a single grain of sugar
white sugar one single piece by itself
in the dark where the heart was then we
imagine keeping our mind on that single
point the body is gone there's no
feeling in the body and there's just the
whole world is a single grain of sugar
where our heart was beating and we put
all our focus all our thoughts into this
single point in a Capgras inside the
grain of sugar try to hold the vision in
your mind of a tiny tiny piece of sugar
white sugar crystal and your mind goes
inside and it stays there super quiet
very very quiet
you
now the fifth level is the we call for
this room and the first part is called
naan khatai infinite space and we
picture a lake huge lake and the surface
is totally quiet calm
not a single ripple and you can feel it
going out to the left and the right I
like to picture it about the level of my
forehead and infinitely wide leg and in
this meditation we in our imagination we
drop like a pebble in the middle of the
lake and then we watch a tiny ripple
moving out on a horizontal plane to the
left and to the right from the center of
our mind and that tiny ripple is
completely silent and it just goes and
goes and goes and there's no shore of
the leg the ripple goes left and right
infinitely and so don't be lazy focus
keep the ripple moving away from you in
your mind to the left and to the right
infinite
moving silent repo
you
now at the sixth level come back to the
center of your mind imagine you're in
the exact center of your mind and a
line is there it's not turned on yet
and when I say go then turn on a tiny
light at the center of your mind and
silently light goes out in all
directions like a expanding ball of
light make it clear light like crystal
this is not the meaning of clear life in
the Buddhism that has a different
meaning of emptiness but this clear
light is like crystal moving out in all
directions
from the center of your mind and I like
to imagine it
keeps going past the atmosphere of this
planet then it envelops the moon and the
Sun and this is the light of my
awareness expanding out way beyond the
Stars and keep it going perfectly silent
ever-expanding okay turn on the light
you
that's a really really really quiet
really silent
but it would be more silent if we could
go to the seventh level please don't
move anything and if we could just turn
off the mind completely like a light
switch just when I say go then just turn
off your mind no thoughts no feelings
nothing as if you your mind was dead and
go into that perfect silence if a
thought comes up then block it turn it
off okay here we go
tell me
you
now to the eighth level the effort to
keep the mind turned off is a kind of
noise in the mind facing thoughts and
memories and feelings turning them off
is like putting out a fire inside your
mind at the eighth level we stop trying
to fight any random thoughts or feelings
that move through the mind so we're
going to turn off the mine shut down the
mine
but if it wakes up and there's little
sparks of thoughts coming through the
mind then we just surrender and we don't
try to resist them or fight them and
this level in tibetan is called do Shan
Mei do shame amen if you can turn off
the mind
turn it off if the mind turns itself on
leave it stay in there silence here we
go
you
now three long exhales don't open your
eyes yet just track three long exhales
you
and then please open your eyes I like to
take a stretch pistol you guys have
microphone Vinny any questions about
that that's just a very beginning good
you too sleepy to ask questions alright
alright let's go to the diamond cutter
Sutra okay then we're studying
commentary by kamila Sheila he lived in
same time as Swanson I guess tongue ciao
seven seven fifty Stanley ad something
like that and but his book didn't reach
China because I think he lived at the
same time as France on and it did reach
to that around
800 years ago and then the Sanskrit
disappeared and we don't have the
Sanskrit we're looking for it we have a
team in India looking for it and we have
a team looking for it online and they
haven't found it yet
someone reconstructed it from the
Tibetan but of course we don't know if
it's correct so we've been going through
the commentary page by page verse by
verse and now we've reached the fourth
class this is the last class about
Camila Sheila and we are following
certain meditations that he recommends
and on the other parts of the diamond
cutter Sutra because the ending is so
important there's a poem at the end and
because it's the most important part of
the diamond cutter Sutra I thought we
should do it first and we'll start
tonight I think we can finish it in two
or three classes and because you can
meditate about it okay it's tomorrow and
the next thing the next day and I'll
give you some meditations you can do
based on karma Sheena okay so I'm going
to teach you those verses this verse and
I had a suggestion that everybody could
memorize their Sanskrit it's not hard we
sang it yesterday day before we it's you
can sing it in about one second that
economy
okay and then I'd like everyone to
memorize the Chinese because that's even
older than the Tibetan Stanley yeah you
put it in the back but that's just a
pronunciation in the Chinese is they
didn't translate but this is just
pronunciation of the Sanskrit no wait
what yeah no I want the Chinese pinyin
can you prepare it for tomorrow then I'd
like everyone to memorize this so don't
memorize this last page that's the gist
a sound in Chinese so but the sounds
good is here on the last page okay you
can memorize that you have to finish by
tomorrow night I'm going to check it's
easy come on just a cup of memorize 30
pages a day this is for blinds okay okay
and then Chinese English of course and
the student who memorized the Tibetan
get extra point okay but by the time by
the end of the week I want to hear those
three from everybody sounds good Chinese
and English Tibetan you can get extra
credit I will give you a big yellow hat
okay so let's start I like to study the
Sanskrit to me it's very beautiful in
Buddhism we say that all Buddha's speak
Sanskrit well everywhere every world ok
so I'm going to pronounce it correctly
and you can repeat after me okay starter
car
demiran depo my of us Avishai but
buddham okay we've been mispronouncing
that everybody okay say but budem okay
Swapna videoed a brown Chuck ever just
of your Sanskrit um okay cool and I'm
gonna teach it to you very slow and very
nice and we're gonna use like five
commentaries okay by the end of this
week you will be sick of this but you
won't know it better than anybody in the
world okay and this is the essence of
the diamond cutter suture okay so I
thought I would start with each time
there are nine parts here nine famous
examples of emptiness and impermanence
okay and I'll first I'll teach you this
Sanskrit and then I'll give it the
meaning from many commentaries okay
we'll start with Vasa bundle which is
seventeen hundred years ago who wrote
the abhidhamma kosha
and then we'll go to
Camila Sheila thirteen hundred years ago
and then we'll do some times with you I
edema from eighteen hundred years ago
and then Tony Lama from about four
hundred years ago and then three other
important Tibetan commentary commentary
commentators one is named John Shiva one
is named $10 Amba and one is named coins
you're tempted to me and I'll introduce
them to you okay I like cognate cognate
means Sanskrit is the mother of Latin
and Greek and they are the mother of all
Western languages European languages and
they are the mother of English so every
almost every Sanskrit word has a
corresponding English word and I think
it will help you to remember the
Sanskrit if I teach you the English
cognate means related English word okay
so and I like cognates if you understand
sounds good well it's a generation of
grammar it you can predict how sounds
good evolves it's it evolved logically
and it means you can take the New York
you can take a newspaper and you can see
the Sanskrit there on every every word
if you know Sanskrit well you can work
backwards you can translate it into
Sanskrit in your mind in a few minutes
some New York Times it's cool okay so
let's start with article
I made this simple for you okay there
are long a shore days
we're not gonna do that I'll just say
Tonica okay da roca means star okay in
the sky the tibetan word is karma so
don't be confused karma of course in
sanskrit means seeds but karma in
tibetan has no relation to karma and
sanskrit karma and tibetan means star
okay tara means to cross over and the
angel who helps you cross over a son
surah is called Daraa okay just the word
of Torah the name Torah that this
Buddhist lady Buddha tarah her name
means cross over and the English word
transportation or transit trend trans
means to cross over okay
so God means doer tariqa means cross her
over okay traveler it means traveler and
in ancient times the stars were called
travelers because they travel on the
same circle or all night okay
they travel in Tibetan is called GU
Cargill car means that travel on the
track all night okay so tariqa means
traveler cross the one who crosses
and we're gonna have nine different
messages here I like to call them nine
messages the first one is the world
around you is like a star okay the world
around you is like a star okay
the world around you the word here is
Sun skirt them
okay the last word Sun scriptum means
the world around you okay
ker the route curve who can tell me no
well ultimately it means to do to do
something karma comes from that okay
okay I are that route in Sanskrit means
to do something in English cognate come
on create I'll kiss you but where are
you who was that
yeah you already have a boyfriend create
serial comes from that which is why it's
done with a sea because it grows crops
and Crescent comes from that like the if
you look at the moon tonight
Crescent means it's growing
okay so ker means to grow Sun means
together
and it came in to Greek as sym and it
came into Latin as Co n so what do you
call a gathering
what do you call in Greek a place where
you gather together synagogue okay
what's the Sanskrit Sangha okay Sangha
the Jewish name for church comes from
Sanskrit Sangha
okay synagogue comes from Sangha okay so
son means together like CLM in committee
or words like that coming together
compose many many English words okay
so sin means together curve means make
and there's a rule in Sanskrit when you
have a M followed by a K you have to put
it s between okay so it's called son
skirt dumb Sanskrit them
what's one meaning of Sanskrit uh-huh
well spoken and it's a language okay
Sanskrit is a bad bad pronunciation of
Sanskrit
okay so Sanskrit the word Sanskrit means
put together well and the language is
perfect okay son skirt it's not stance
grid okay
that's like Moscow instead of the real
word is what Moscow ah okay okay it's
Sanskrit ah okay now sounds good it
means anything that's put together by
causes so it means all the stuff around
you the world everything in your world
the people you know the things you see
are called Sanskrit and the Buddha
compares all the things in your life to
nine different things the first one is
star everything in your life is like a
star now starting with Lhasa bunder they
organized these nine into four groups
okay these nine example starting with
star they are they are put into four
groups okay if you're really gonna
understand the cheng anjing you have to
understand the last poem and to
understand that for for one thousand
seven hundred years they divided these
nine into four groups
okay here's the for you ready I know you
had jet lag I don't care I have it all
year except here me and mr. Wu we we
live on jet lag we eat jet length for
breakfast okay first one first group
first three examples first three
examples okay this is called how is your
world you know like what what's the
what's your world like what's your world
really like okay people places what are
they really like okay that's the first
group how many first three first three
examples
Terrica terminal and depot these three
are what's your world like okay what's
your world like three examples by Buddha
okay now the fourth one stands by itself
okay say Maya what's Maya illusion okay
or magic trick okay illusion Maya okay
that one stands by itself and it's an
answer to the question of how do I taste
the world how do I taste my world okay
how do I taste it so ever since vasa
fondue up to now that's the second group
how many members in the second group one
good okay how many members in the first
group nice first group is what's your
world like second group is how do you
taste your world how do you taste your
one third group two members what's wrong
with your world okay what's wrong with
your world which are which are the two
images appear of a shia of shia okay now
in sanskrit when an ami-chan a they join
so when you sing it you say my of a shia
my yamaha Shire but really it's two
separate words maya of a shire
but in sanskrit when Amy's a you joined
together and you're supposed to make it
longer my yama shia my Avishai okay well
i'm not gonna teach you that but in
classical Sanskrit poetry you have to
give it double length my Yahveh shia
okay and then the dumb but budem no
relation to buddha okay it's a it means
a bubble and we're not we're not
studying that yeah okay those two of ash
of a shia and booed buddha these two
tell you what yeah what's wrong with
your world what's wrong with your world
okay how many we have now we have three
one and two good trailer okay which is
Swapna video and Abram okay this last
three okay they are reason why you
should escape from this world a reason
why you should escape from this world
okay Wheel of Life
the last three are reason to escape from
the world of life the Wheel of Life
okay why you should get out okay it's
kind of related to the third group third
group is problems right fourth group
means why you should be tired of this
life okay why you should want to get out
okay so these are nine examples in four
groups
okay got it okay we'll talk more about
it every day okay but now we're gonna go
to the first group how many members
what's it about what's your world like
what is your word like and the first of
them is a star okay alright good okay so
I have a plan each each of the nine I'm
gonna tell you how many different things
you can think about during your
meditation okay so each of the nine I
will say inside here there's five things
to think about or inside here there are
six things to think about and then
you're gonna meditate on them okay so
your job starting tonight we still have
half an hour I'm sorry you jetlag guys
I'm sending you to bed early okay
get you Michael when he go - engine or
Berlin he has to stay up till midnight
the first night Singapore - give me a
three interviews with TV after the talk
okay so each of the nine messages has
many different parts okay and those are
going to be your meditation guide so you
have two meditations this
you're gonna practice that this is a
good way to wake you up okay sound like
a lion no oh okay you're gonna practice
seeing that Benjamin betta okay lion
stance and then you're gonna do the jig
anjing
diamond cutter sutra meditations okay
and just this verse will take you the
whole week okay just this verse will
take you go homie okay trust me you know
you can throw out this already okay
Tim's like are we paid for that okay
don't worry about it
okay okay star has six different
meanings okay the star has six different
meanings and each time I teach you a
meaning I'm gonna give you some of the
people who taught it just their names
okay just their names these are your
family these are your great-grandparents
these are your llama grandparents okay
you should know them okay when you study
Tantra here at Diamond Mountain which is
the best place in the world to study
Tundra you will become generation number
44 am i right okay and you have to
memorize the first 43 names okay
then when we get to Ella we'll go
you know your students have to okay so
it's good if you know the names of your
parents right lineage okay so here's the
position of first one how many six okay
six different meanings of star six
different meanings of star you won't get
this explanation anywhere in the world
so enjoy okay
then teach it to people learn it and
teach it to people okay so this is the
position of vassal bundle and Kamla
Sheena and Tony Romo okay those three
big llamas and John me young shepherd
George Jung young shepherd dorje I'll
tell you about him okay
born 1648 died 1721 monks name not long
syndrome and I listened to the recording
okay he was the abbot of one of the
Abbott's of gable monastery okay Goemon
college thirty second era and he's cool
because after he finished his Geshe
degree he went back home to east to bet
and he made a monastery called la brown
dashiki oh okay LeBron labrang monastery
very famous it's one of the great gloop
Oh monasteries in east of it and he also
went to give me a tender college there
are two tantric colleges in tibetan
goethe and give me which one are you
you argue me okay we are give me an
image my lama was vice a bit of cumin so
he went he finished you may attend to
college
and he was ayrton in Omaha which is
means the mango king gave him a special
title okay Aaron in Omaha okay big Lama
very very cool extremely cool Lama
his stuff is unbelievable okay now
here's their position
all those guys ready here's what they
say the star means star can only shine
at night and what's the second husband
means somebody explain second husband to
me huh okay on Wednesday you yell at
your kids on Monday you go to work you
come home you open the door your husband
yells at you before you say anything
okay then natural reaction I didn't do
anything I get three they start yelling
at me okay then this is natural human
reaction okay is it true I didn't do
anything
no you yelled at your kids last week who
heard you your kids heard you and you
heard you when you hear yourself that
plans Karma
okay when you see yourself give money
you plant karma and it makes an
impression on your mind and and that
becomes a comma C okay so last week you
you yelled at your kids because they
didn't go to school on time then you
made many impressions on your mind and
then this week when you came home you
open the door you didn't say anything I
didn't do anything
husband's start yelling on you where's
the husband come from coming from here
okay coming from seed coming from right
here seeds opening husband's coming out
okay
why
because you yelled at your kids our last
week okay but we don't understand that
so when we come home we think the
husband is mean and the husband is bad
and I didn't do anything he's yelling at
me okay
what's the human reaction let's say the
husband call you stupid
what's the human reaction I'm not stupid
you're stupid okay
then what happened you are stupid you
plant another seed next week your kids
will be bad come from sitting then you
say your stupid kids plant another seed
then the next week your husband call you
stupid again okay what's the human
reaction when the husband calls stupid
I'm not stupid you're stupid how can you
prove you're stupid say stupid back ok
then your husband is correct you are
stupid okay cuz you call him stupid
actually you should go to the toilet
close the door
look in the mirror you are stupid that's
correct
got it so in DCI training we say there
are always two husbands living in your
house who are they one comes from you
okay a trained a person who came to
Diamond Mountain and got trained when
they go home to China or Russia or
Germany or Mexico and their husband says
then they go okay okay got it they
understand the husband comes from them
they understand got it okay
I'm sorry they understand the husband
come from there then they don't accept
the second husband who's the second
husband he decide to call me stupid he
come from his side which one exists yeah
the one that comes from me exist are you
saying the
husband who come this way doesn't exist
are you telling me that
yeah that's correct he's the absence of
that husband is called Kong Ching
emptiness okay got it
so there's two husbands in your house
what is real he come from what you said
to the kids last week okay that that
husband is real but there's a second
husband who what it do they say come on
Nick come on help me on he just woke up
never existed
never will exist and cannot exist now
there's second husband in your house
never existed will never exist and
cannot exist now okay
impossible the absence of that husband
has come Antonis okay now we got two
husbands in your house one come from you
he's real okay the other one you always
thought he decided to call you stupid
that one doesn't exist okay the one who
come from his own time who decided to
call you stupid that one doesn't exist
everybody clearly now which one do you
get upset on yeah the second one thought
he doesn't make fist okay your whole
life every time you got have said that
husband didn't exist the one you're
upset at never existed okay got it
he's the star King he's this star in
he's dead Terrica okay so when you see
taka and you explain it to your own
students you say I'm gonna teach you the
sons right Tonica it means second
husband in your house didn't everybody
say well tell me more I would like to
have a second husband okay
the husband who doesn't exist is the
star okay now you tell me
that husband can only live if there is
darkness who said that I would kiss you
but your yellow beard I wish you anyway
okay that's star of the husband who
doesn't exist can only live in the
darkness okay if there's darkness
darkness doesn't understand this husband
come from me I yelled at my kiss last
week okay
that's darkness I'm sorry if you don't
understand that that's darkness oh I
don't do anything that's darkness okay
and in that darkness can live the star
now what happens if the Sun comes up
Boop what's the Sun ah he come from me
yeah go ahead call me stupid it's okay
I've just used up my bad seed you want
to call me stupid some more II just I
want to use them my best come on just
get it all get all the seeds out like
that okay got it when the Sun comes up
the star cannot be seen okay the sec the
husband who didn't come from you which
is the star you cannot see it when the
Sun comes up Sun is one wisdom bottle
below middle Presnell parameter okay
wisdom that whole long word perfection
of wisdom just forget it
it means I understand the second husband
our first husband I don't know okay I
understand my husband I have progeny
paramita okay forget all those long
Buddhist words I hate them dependent
origination
it means husband come from you that's
all okay got it
if the Sun comes up you cannot see the
star the stars the husband who doesn't
exist
what's the category what category we in
yeah what's your world like you are
surrounded by stars you want to know
what your world is like you are
surrounded by people who irritate you
who hurt you who cut you off in traffic
who call you bad names stars all around
you like a diamond mountain night okay
there's a famous joke here the lady came
from Shanghai she's first night she's
like oh lady stars you know then she
asked Michael Dunn will they be here
tomorrow yeah they're here every night
okay okay
but you are surrounded by stars what
does it mean every time you have a bad
experience you blame it on the other
person okay you live in the stars you
live surrounded by stars turn on the Sun
okay next time someone upsets you Oh
somebody said something bad about Casey
Mike on internet game stupid Princeton
you know then I just plant another one
okay got it
Geshe Michael just learn what you're
teaching okay I'm trying okay yeah I
surrounded my star use the Sun turn the
Sun uh-huh I know you're coming from me
I'm gonna shut up then you'll disappear
okay got it
beautiful that's the first of the six
meanings ready okay
first one
[Music]
this might take a few years we have time
for yeah we have some time okay the
second one I'm gonna give you is from a
llama named $10 Amba $10 and balarama
means highest cachet highest takeshi
degree I'm the lowest okay I'm a ling
say I just barely made it then they say
you want to go for my I said no I'm done
somebody takes another 10 years I'm like
I got things to do
okay I'm a Geisha that's enough okay
1759 1831 monk named long tender
nickname a lock shut and our election
means like Bowie okay probably a little
bigger like Wilkins
yeah anyway I'm not gonna make jokes
about he was Mongolian he studied at
debunk among monastery and one of his
Lamas was the great long de lama he's a
very famous historian and blood writer
and cartoonish Johnson and and he was
such a good debater that they just
called him it's like calling him Geshe
Michael or he just they just call
him/her Amba it means like big big dish
they called him big caches whole life
he said no no no the stars are the truth
of suffering first of the four truths of
Buddhism okay
the stars in this verse are the truth of
suffering okay now there's something you
have to understand Buddha said all of my
teaching can be summarized in four
truths they are mistranslated as Noble
Truths they are not Noble no it's a bad
translation of ayah okay
therefore Arya truth because our EEOC's
they are true whose Arya anyone who saw
emptiness directly is called aya okay
so they are for aya truth if you ever
call them noble truth I will squeeze
your noble neck okay completely bad
translation for 200 years in America
okay let's try to kill those bad
translations okay for aya truth okay so
he said the stars are truth of suffering
now you have to know something about the
truth of suffering okay usually truth
means you know if this rosary is has
less mass than the earth then it will
fall when I let go if it has more mass
than the earth the earth will fall up
when I let go okay like that okay so
usually in English and in Sanskrit okay
Satya truth means this is this there
should be a is right this is this okay
the first truth should be all things are
suffering or something like that all
changing things are pain that should be
the first truth but it's not the pain
itself is called the truth of suffering
if I pinch you I just gave you truth of
sorry
you can call it true suffering real
suffering so the four truths are not
statements they are not true ideas
they're not they are the thing itself
pain is the first truth okay pain itself
someone pinch you it's the first truth
okay
so $10 Amba said you want to know what
the star means it means all the things
in your life which are giving you pain
that's the Stars that's the story okay
all the things in your life that are
giving you pain and he says the real
sunlight is the direct perception of
emptiness by an aria okay the real
emptiness by an aria and at that moment
the stars cannot shine okay why there's
no suffering at that moment okay there's
no suffering there's a path and there's
cessation there's the end of suffering
there's the end of suffering and there's
the path his mind is the path his or her
mind is the path the coaching is the end
of suffering okay so for the first time
no stars
for the first time in your life no stars
garden you okay that's the second
meaning okay everybody is living
surrounded by stars all the time because
everything in your life can hurt you
okay everything in your life can all Sun
skirt thumbs anything that has a cause
can hurt you okay got it
but if you turn on that light during
meditation on level 9 in your cabin
tomorrow
the first time you turn out the Stars
okay
first time you turn out the Stars okay
got it
that's the second one how we got time we
just do one more okay let me really
torture you yeah
send your ultimate cause my Mexican
friend call me mister oh just one more
thing okay
third one by coin shot Tembe during a
coin Jordan to me it's a famous Lama
born in 1762 died 1823 this llamas by
the way they wrote commentaries on this
poem they wrote commentaries on this
poem okay beautiful commentaries okay
and Buddha taught this verse several
other times and I will teach you those
okay I can teach it to you for a week if
you want he taught at other places and
he taught at different ways and because
of Nick and John Brady we have that all
in the database we should give them a
hand
[Applause]
so for dessert at the end of teacher a
little bit about how Buddha taught it in
other places okay not just in the where
garden of prints Jetta you forget how
much she loved one when I teach comes
here - I know okay question Emma Germain
born in LA Brown sorry
he was the 21st abbot of Lebrun who
founded Lebrun Johnny shape but we
already heard about him by the way I
checked how close to Xian not far from
Shyam that monastery is a about 300
miles 350 miles like my house - here -
dr. Wu's main place it's the same
distance you can drive there in one day
I guess so
that monastery founded in 1709 now it's
in gansu province it's about 400 miles
west of Xian which is she's shy she
promised he also studied at Devon gamma
and he wrote a commentary to two famous
prayers one is this terracotta manam
deep oh okay
and he wrote a commentary the same
commentary is a commentary on sabotaging
your jaws and gettin the job done became
the launch engine cheetah technician
which are Wheel of Life the verse at the
bar he wrote a commentary on both of
them okay
at the same time why
because monks and nuns are supposed to
say these two verses every two weeks
when they confess come out of mm in the
gilma Supercheap in the middle or until
number do teach in and at the top and
we're supposed to snap our finger
it means we maybe we die before the next
time we meet you know life life is quick
okay so it's part of the monks and nuns
sodium these two verses so he wrote a
commentary on them okay very beautiful
all right he says this represents Nong
Tom say no Tony don't you know tongba
Kong Xin emptiness okay none means the
world that appears to you the world as
it appears to you okay literally it
means bright nun means everything you
see in your life is called nun
everything that appears to you in this
world your whole life whole life
appearing to you is called nun in
Buddhism there are two parts to the
world none and tongue saying none
don't the appearance of the world and
the emptiness of the world okay what
what do you think's in other word for a
nun
yeah dependent generation okay anything
comes from causes the appearing to
people places world your your own body
is none okay
tall means higher reality emptiness okay
higher now he says by the way there's
another word from num what is it
do you know remember Princip Demba fake
reality fake reality then there's denim
demo true reality
so Buddhism says there's two realities
fake reality and real me okay we are
living in fake reality in the fake
reality it looks like your husband is
angry at you that's called fake reality
is it real yeah I'm sorry is it is it
reality is it in your house yes
is it real no it's fake your mind makes
it okay there's there's no husband who's
coming from your husband okay so there's
normal reality then there's ultimate
reality okay you can't have fake reality
unless you have real reality okay this
is fake butter
it means somewhere there should be some
real butter
okay when you say fake it means there's
a there's a real one somewhere okay
what's another fake this is fake give me
another thing huh a fake diamond this is
a fake diamond it means there should she
was in the diamond business then it
means there should be a real diamond
somewhere okay so the fake one is fake
compared to the real okay the star can
only appear in the darkness okay Garlan
darkness means emptiness in his in his
interpretation the darkness is emptiness
and the star is normal reality
okay what we call nun don't know is the
star
that's what appears to you people places
cars cities countries your own body okay
it's the star and it can only exist in
an empty world you see black got it
that's that's his interpretation the
fake reality can only exist in the width
in the background there's a real reality
okay got it
what appears to you in your life your
whole life is the star but the
background reality that allows the start
of shine is conching is emptiness
sometimes they call crunchy right the
foundation reality
okay okay got it you okay you guys okay
cat got it she's like on a diamond
cutter drug tonight she's at war
by the way I mean you want to go deeper
you got three minutes okay I'm gonna
take you deeper a Chinese people like to
go deeper who would say that if you
cancel the fake part of changing things
you get reality if you were in Shenzhen
recently you should know mind only mind
only
okay this is mind only score classic
mind only score okay
classic mind only school take all the
changing things in the world subtract
the fake part and you get Kong Ching and
these are the three parts of the mind on
the school these are the three
characteristics of the mind on the
school
that's what Buddha taught during the
witch turning of the wheel third turning
of the real okay people said in the
second term you said anything's empty is
that crazy he said yeah I was just
kidding okay got it
so this position is very close to mind
only school what none the star is all
the normal stuff in the world okay and
it's faint cancel the fake you got
emptiness okay the darkness so for him
the darkness is a good thing okay in the
last two guys the darkness was a bad
thing ignorance yeah got it
cool yeah okay that's the third guy all
right let's stop there we got three more
just in the first of the nine okay got
it
we are discussing the way things are
around
we didn't get to the way we taste it we
didn't get to the problems of it and we
didn't get to how you should escape it
okay and we still have a few hundred
pages of commentary to look at but I
don't think we will finish this poem by
the way I'm ready to teach you that if
you're gonna paint in the counter but
well let's see how much we can get to
you'll be the only people in the world
who really understand this verse I think